Guide to the Ward College of Technology records ARCH072
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Ward College of Technology records
1948-2009
Undated
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Ward College of Technology
ARCH072
6.34 Linear Feet (23 containers)
The collection consists of records from the Ward College of Technology from 1948 to 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to all researchers.
Historical Note
Adapted from the Ward College of Technology Website in 2006:
The Ward School was an early affiliated college of the University of Hartford. The College has had a long and complex history and has been known by many different names. In 2003 the College of Engineering and Ward, by then known as the Ward College of Technology, merged to become the College of Engineering, Technology and Architecture (CETA).. The origins of Ward begin with the vision of Hartford industrialist Samuel I. Ward, president of Crystal Research Laboratories (CRL). During Ward War II, CRL emerged as leading supplier of specialized electronic devices, including piezoelectric crystals. The post-war expansion of the electronics industry created a new opportunity for CRL. Anticipating a growing need for skilled technicians to serve the youthful industry, Mr. Ward formed CRL School of Electronics in 1948. On February 24, 1948, the school opened with a class of 75. The school prospered and soon outgrew its original training session. In 1952, Mr. Ward gave the school to Hillyer College to secure its continued development as an educational institution. At this time, the school was renamed the Ward School of Electronics and moved to 44 Niles Street. In 1957, Hillyer merged with the Hartford Art School and the Hartt School of Music to create the University of Hartford. Ward's academic programs grew apace with the development of the profession and remained at the forefront of engineering technology education. In 1964, it established an associate degree program and became Ward Technical Institute. Fifteen years later, Ward created Connecticut's only baccalaureate-level program in Electronic Engineering Technology. In 1971-72, the Institute became Samuel I. Ward Technical College. In the fall of 1972, the College moved to East Hall on the University's campus. Ward's portfolio was further expanded in 1982 with the addition of an associate degree program in Computer Engineering Technology. The associate and baccalaureate programs in Electronic Engineering Technology are accredited by the Technology Accreditation Commission of the Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology. Effective September 1, 1986, the University's Board of Regents changed the College's name to Samuel I. Ward College of Technology to better reflect the roles which its graduates play in business and industry, the increasing sophistication of its programs, and the growing professionalism of engineering technology. September 1991 the Ward College of Technology began a baccalaureate degree program in Architectural Engineering Technology as the start of its mission to diversify and increase the number of technologies offered by the College. The Architectural Engineering technology program is also accredited by the Technology Accreditation Commission of the Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology. In 1992, the College announced the establishment of a baccalaureate program in Mechanical Engineering Technology, to commence in the fall of 1993. In 1995, the College added a baccalaureate program in Audio Engineering Technology and the Computer Engineering Technology Major added a baccalaureate level. Chemical Engineering Technology followed the following year. In 1998 Ward College of Technology celebrated the 50th anniversary of its founding. In 1999 Ward College assumed management of the Connecticut Space Grant Consortium. In 2003 the College of Engineering and the Ward College of Technology merged to become the College of Engineering, Technology and Architecture. Also in 2003 construction of ISET, Integrated Science, Engineering and Technology (ISET) complex began construction. In the fall of 2004 the Master of Architecture program began.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, reports, memorandums, printed ephemera, meeting minutes, photographs, and audio-visual recordings from the Ward College of Technology from 1948 until its merger with the College of Engineering in 2003.
The majority of the collection consists of subject files which cover topics ranging from joining Hillyer College, planning facility spaces, accreditation and self-study reports and other documentation pertaining to the operations of the school, to histories written about the school and anniversary celebrations. Faculty meeting minutes from 1985-2003 are also a sizeable portion of the collection.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series: I. Subject Files, II. Ward Faculty Meeting Minutes, III. Photographs, IV. Recordings, V. Artifacts, and VI. Duplicates.
Photographs; minutes (administrative records); Correspondence; Video recordings; Sound recordings; Buildings; Scrapbooks; Ward College of Technology; Ward School of Electronics; Hadad, Alan; Gehman, Chester; Ward, Samuel I.; Hillyer College; University of Hartford; Lescarbeau, Roland F.; Crystal Research Laboratories; Crystal Research Laboratories.. School of Electronics; Ward Technical Institute; Samuel I. Ward Technical College; Samuel I. Ward College of Technology
- Subject Files, 1948-2009; Undated
  - Accreditation, 1952-2001 (Box Subject Files 1, Folder 1-7)
    Scope and Contents
    This file consists primarily of correspondence and reports created in preparation for, and as a result of, various accreditations including from the Engineers' Council for Professional Development. Additional information regarding Self-studies can be found in the Self-Study file.
  - Administration, 1953 (Box Subject Files 1, Folder 8)
  - Alumni Directory, 1949-1964 (Box Subject Files 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1967,1985 (Box Subject Files 1, Folder 10-11)
  - A.S.S.E Centennial, 1991-1992; 1985 (Box Subject Files 1, Folder 12)
  - A Brief History of Practice and Planning at the University of Hartford, 1955-1983 (Box Subject Files 1, Folder 13)
  - Brochures, 1952-1960, Undated; Undated (Box Subject Files 1, Folder 14, Box Subject Files 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Budget, 1952-1970 (Box Subject Files 2, Folder 3)
  - Building, 1960-1973; Undated (Box Subject Files 2, Folder 4-7, Box Shared Oversized 2)
  - Case Satement, Circa 1970 (Box Subject Files 2, Folder 8)
  - Changes;Improvements, 1952-1953 (Box Subject Files 2, Folder 9)
  - Christmas Dance, Undated (Box Subject Files 2, Folder 10)
  - Circle K Thanksgiving Project, 1968 (Box Subject Files 2, Folder 11)
  - Commencement Programs, 1952-1971 (Box Subject Files 2, Folder 12)
  - Commencement Ritual, 1988 May 15 (Box Subject Files 2, Folder 13)
  - Conference, 1963 (Box Subject Files 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondances, 1954-1967 (Box Subject Files 2, Folder 15-18, Box Subject Files 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Crystal Research Laboratories, 1951-1958 (Box Subject Files 3, Folder 3-5)
  - Curriculum, 1961-1968 Jun, Undated; Undated (Box Subject Files 3, Folder 6-8)
  - Dean Hadad, 1989 Sep 01 (Box Subject Files 3, Folder 9)
  - Diplomas, 1961-1962 (Box Subject Files 3, Folder 10)
  - Educational Specifications, 1964 (Box Subject Files 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Electron Beam, 1952,1962 (Box Subject Files 3, Folder 13)
  - Ward School of Electronics, 1958-1963 (Box Subject Files 3, Folder 14-16)
  - Electro-Mechanical, Engineering, and Technology Proposal, 1965 (Box Subject Files 3, Folder 17)
  - Electronic Engineering Technology Program, 1964 Jan (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 1)
  - Enrollment, 1954-1969 (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Fellows, Douglas M., 1955-1968 (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 4-6)
  - Future Structure of the College of Engineering and Ward School, 2003 (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 7)
  - Gateway and Aetna Ward Programs for High School Students, 1986 (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 8, Folder OV Folder 1)
    Consists of press releases and promotional information about the Gateway and Aetna programs. Includes a oversized University of Hartford poster.
  - Gehman, Chester, 1972; 1992 (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 9)
  - General Electric, 1960 (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 10)
  - Ground Breaking Address and Remarks, 1970 Aug 26 (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 11)
  - Happenings, 1991-2002 (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 12)
  - History, 1952-1992, Undated (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 13-17)
  - Income, 1952-1963 (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 18)
  - Industrial Advisory Committee, 1963-1967 (Box Subject Files 4, Folder 19)
  - Institute of Electric and Electronics Engineers, Undated (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 1)
  - Interim Developments Final Reports, Undated (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 2)
  - Kinsella School, 1962 Jan-May (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 3)
  - Legal Agreements and Certificates, 1952 (Box Subject Files 7, Folder 9)
  - Lescarbeau, Roland, 1964-1966; 1972 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Schedule of National Science Foundation Programs, 1963 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 6)
  - New Campus Site, 1955; 1957 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 7, Box Shared Oversized 2)
  - Ward School News Clips, 1961-1971 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 8)
  - Newsletter, 1959 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 9)
  - Notes from the desk of Wilson and Lescarbeau, Undated (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 10)
  - Physics, 1968-1978 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 11)
  - Planning, 1964 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 12)
  - Poems for the season: D.M Fellows, 1968 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 13)
  - Policy, 1958-1959 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 14)
  - Ward Press Release, 1952 Jun-Jul; 1971-1979 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 15-16)
  - Progress Report, 1969 Mar (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 17)
  - Project Manual for a Laboratory and Classroom Building, 1970 Jun 01 (Box Large Shared Book Tray 1)
  - Proposed Bachelor of Technology Program, 1976; 1978 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 18)
  - Proposal: Need for trained electro-mechanical technicians, 1965-1966 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 19)
  - Publicity, Undated (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 20)
  - Public relations for CRL school of Electronics, Undated (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 21)
  - Rededication, 1986 Oct 21 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 22)
  - Ward School Regulations and Reports, 1962-1964 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 23)
  - Richard Mills, 1993 Feb (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 24)
  - Room Inventory, 1964 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 25)
  - Samuel I Ward's Display and C.R.L, 2009 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 26)
  - Scholarships, Grants, and Awards, 1971, Undated (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 27)
  - Scrapbook, 1948-1952 (Box Shared Small Oversized 3)
  - Self-Study, 1975-1996 (Box Subject Files 5, Folder 28-30, Box Subject Files 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Sellavision, 1960 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 5)
  - Special Events, Celebration of Invention, 1993-1994; 1999 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 6)
  - Statements/Press Releases: A.M Woodruff, 1972 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 7)
  - Studies, Reports, and Correspondences: Alan S. Wilson, 1963-1965 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 8)
  - Ward Technical College-News Clips and Press Releases, 1984-1985 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 9)
  - Need for Technical Education, 1961 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 10)
  - Technical Educational Consortium, 1968 Jun (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 11)
  - Technical Institute Division, 1963,1968 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 12)
  - Ward Technical Institute Purchase Order, Undated (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 13)
  - Trustees, 1972-1977 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 14)
  - Veterans, 1952-1963 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 15)
  - Visitation Committee, 1961 Nov (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 16)
  - Ward's 25th Anniversary, 1972 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 17)
  - Ward's 40th Anniversary, 1988 (Box Subject Files 6, Folder 18)
  - Ward's 50th Anniversary, 1998 (Box Subject Files 7, Folder 1-7)
  - The Ward School Story, 1960 Feb 19 (Box Subject Files 7, Folder 8)
- Ward Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1985 Sep - 2003 May
  - 1985 Sep - 1988 Nov (Box Faculty Meeting Minutes 1)
  - 1989 Jan - 1993 Dec (Box Faculty Meeting Minutes 2)
  - 1994 Jan - 1999 Nov (Box Faculty Meeting Minutes 3)
  - 2000 Jan - 2003 May (Box Faculty Meeting Minutes 4)
- Photographs, 1950-1998; Undated
  - Aetna/ Ward Scholarship Luncheon, 1988 Sep 17 (Box Photographs 1, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Advisory Board, 1988 Feb 27 (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - A.S.S.E. Centennial, 1985 Nov 27 (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Board of Visitors, Undated (Box Photographs 1, Folder 2)
  - Buildings, 1971, Undated (Box Photographs 1, Folder 3)
  - Chester Gehman (Dean), Undated (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Circle K Thanksgiving Project, 1968 (Box Photographs 1, Folder 4)
  - C.R.L/Ward Scrapbook, Circa 1950 (Box Photographs 1, Folder 5)
  - Dedication of Memorial Bench to Professor O'Connell, Undated (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Faulty, Staff, and History Board, 1986-1998; Undated (Box Photographs 1, Folder 6-9, Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Forrest Tyson, 1957 (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - GroundBreaking, 1970 Aug (Box Photographs 1, Folder 10)
  - Lambda Epsilon Chapter Officers, 1987-1988 (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Lescarbeau, Roland F., 1962 Dec; 1972 Feb (Box Photographs 1, Folder 11, Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Marketing Material, Undated (Box Photographs 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorial Bench Dedication, Undated (Box Photographs 1, Folder 13, Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - New Campus Site, 1957 Jun (Box Photographs 1, Folder 14)
  - Newsletter Fall' 94, 1994 (Box Photographs 1, Folder 15)
  - Rededication, 1986 (Box Photographs 1, Folder 16, Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Ron Klimas, Undated (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Scrapbook Photographs, Undated (Box Shared Small Oversized 3)
  - Sellavision, 1960 (Box Photographs 1, Folder 17)
  - Student Council Officers, 1987-1988 (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - U of H Campus Model Installation, Undated (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Ward College Slides, 1971 Sep (Box Photographs 1, Folder 18)
  - Ward exhibits at Niles St., Undated (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Ward Family at 50th Anniversary, 1998 (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Ward Recruiting, 1988 (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Ward School of Electronics, Circa 1950-1970 (Box Photographs 1, Folder 21)
  - Ward School at Niles St., Undated (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - The Ward School Story, 1960 Feb 19 (Box Photographs 1, Folder 22, Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Ward's 40th Anniversary Party, 1988 Feb 24 (Box Photographs 1, Folder 19, Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Ward's 50th Anniversary Photographs, 1998 (Box Photographs 1, Folder 20, Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
  - Windows Installed in East Hall, 1986 (Box Shared Photograph Box 3)
- Recordings, 1960-1998
  - Carnival of Science, Ward School of Electronics, 1960; 1 Reels Supper 8 film, labeled #880 3 inch (Box #860-881)
  - Chester Gehman's audio directions to students leaning to use card-punch computer, donated by IBM, Circa 1960s; 1 Cassettes audio cassette (Box Shared Cassette Box 1)
  - Roland F. Lescarbeau plaque dedication, Ward Technical College, 1972 Nov 11; 1 Cassettes audio cassette (Box Shared Cassette Box 1)
  - Ward College Dedication, 1986 Oct 21; 2 Cassettes audio cassette, appear to be duplicate copies (Box Shared Cassette Box 1)
  - Engineering Technology Beginnings, ASEE Conference, 1987 Jun; 1 Cassettes VHS tape (Box Shared Videotape 1)
  - Ward College and College of Engineering Joint Luncheon, 1998 Jan 15; 1 Reels VHS (Box Shared Videotape 2)
  - Ward 40th Birthday, faculty - new offices tour, Walter and Peggy Roettger's prenuptial party, 1988 Feb 24; 1 Reels VHS (Box Shared Videotape 2)
  - S. I. Ward College of Technology 50th Anniversary, Hartford Golf Club, 1998 Feb 24; 2 Cassettes UMatic, recording appears to be in two parts (Box Shared UMatic 1)
  - S. I. Ward College, 50th Anniversary Celebration, 1998; 2 Reels VHS, duplicates (Box Shared Videotape 2)
  - Ward College 50th Anniversary, 1998; 2 Cassettes One VHS and One UMatic, unclear if duplicates or not (Box Shared Videotape 2, Box Shared UMatic 1)
- Artifacts, 1972-1999; Undated
  - Chester Gehman's teaching tape for television signal demonstration, 1972 (Artifacts Box 11, Object 0207303183389)
  - Ward College of Technology felt-tip pen, 1999 (Artifacts Box 11, Object 0207303183280)
    Related Materials
    Pen moved from the subject file "Special Events, Celebration of Invention."
  - Ward Technical College Resistor Color Code Card, Undated (Artifacts Box 11)